This program is presented by University of California Television
Like what you learn? Visit our website or follow us on facebook and twitter to keep up with the latest UCTV program
Good evenening every one. Welcome again to our penultimate class in this semesters' course in nutrition
a reminder that next week we will be talking about vitamins and minerals and vitamin and mineral supplements so please join us for that last class
Dr Jeffrey Thais will be the professor joining us that evening
tonight we have what I guess for some of you has been the lecture you've been waiting for since the beginning
Dr Lustig gave a similar lecture in 2009
little did we know at the time that it would have 3.5 million downloads
since then ? in this room at a course very similar to this that I also cheared ?
and it's really... I think changed his life more than anything else but I think the hope is, that… it's also
changed the field and the topic and the policies and the politics that we are going to talk about tonight
many of you know Dr. Lustig is an internationally known neuroendicronologist in pediatrics
he trained for part of his time at UCSF then went back east to do a clinical neuroendicronology and came back to UCSF in 2001
where he's continued to do his clinical science
on factors that control appetite, particularly the interaction between
the hormones of insulin, leptin, grellin,
and appetite control and metabolic syndrome and obesity
more recently… in part around the time of the video and certainly in the four years since
Rob has become an international leader
in the efforts to improve our nutrition not only in the United States but around the world
he's focused a larger part by putting a real microscope on the issues of
fructose and sugar in general and refined foods in general
the relationship of the dieatary fiber and the many of the other topics
that we've been talking about over the course of the course
Rob just returned from Europe
this morning, in fact arrived here at 5 o'clock this evening
we think he had dinner, we know he hasn't had sleep, it's 4 o'clock Europe time for him so
this was really a heroic effort
our fingers were crossed that all the flights would be on time
and I'm very pleased more than you can imagine
that he's here tonight, 'cause I didn't wanna give this lecture as well
but in addition to his work, Rob recently took a sabbatical
in order to further this work and spend a large part of that time at his ? school of law
giving a Master of studies in Law
and part of his aspiration I think is really to aid his legal training now
to his science and medical training
to continue to advocate for good nutrition around the world so
we're very anxious to hear about his newest thoughts on this topic
we've entitled the talk the same title as his best selling book
"Fat Chance" and added the subtitle "Fructose 2.0", Rob
Thank you Bobby and thank all of you for coming, you know, to some extent this is sort of like dejavu all over again
you know having done this 4 years ago and it really did change my life and hopefully changed a few peoples' lifes
in the audience and certainly around the world
I still get emails from that video today, ah, you know, people who've seen it for the first time
that video we are gonna refer back to it in some, to some extent tonight
'cause I am not gonna redo the biochemestry, there's no point in doing it twice
what we're gonna talk tonight about is primarily the physiology
so, in essence, the two videos will end up being complementary on youtube
and hopefully people who watch it will end up watching both, so keep that in mind
all right, well, a lot happened in four years, and the data just keeps rolling in, and unfortunately for us all the data is pretty awful
so you'll see why as we go and I will try to delineate that as we go
so first of all I have no disclosures, no food industry is putting me up to this
you be sure of that
so here's the past, this is 2001
6 million kids are seriously overwheight, well
with all of the media attention, with all of the NAH money, with all of the clinical programs
and with Michelle Obama's vegetable gardens we are now up to 20 million
here's the present
currently there are 30 percent more obese people on the planet than undernourished people
and this has happened only within 15 years because 15 years ago was exactly the opposite
and it's occurring in countries that still have under nutrition
so how do you explain that, other than to say
that can't be behaviour, that's gotta be an exposure
this looks like any standard pandemic
influenza, typhoid, etc
this looks like a microbial phenomenon rather than a behavioral phenomenon, we're gonna go there
366 million diabetics walking the earth, that's 5 percent of the worlds' population
and they are chewing through all the health-care resources
this was just three months ago, diabetics cost the US 24 billion dollars
now if we could recoup even a fraction of that we wouldn't even need health-care reform
in fact it's been suggested that we wouldn't even need financial reform
ok, 41 percent rise in 5 years, this is going up so fast it makes your head spin
and here's the future if we do nothing
experts predict 165 million Americans, 42 percent would be obese by the year 2030
100 million Americans, that'll be 33 percent, will have diabetes by 2050
but fear not, because it won't really matter because Medicare will be broke by 2026
so, as the Soup Nazi once said: "No health-care for you"
well, the fact of the matter is, I'm gonna be 69 in 2026 and I want my fricking Medicare
and… so should you all
the point is, we have to do something different, and you know the old adage, right?
the definition of insanity is doing the same thing over and over again and expecting a different result
well I'm here to tell you for the last 30 years we've done the same thing over and over and over again
and there has been no change in the result
so we have to rethink this, we have to reframe the argument and that's what we are gonna try to do tonight
and I'm'a doit right now
so here's the way people view this issue
this is a Venn diagram of all the adults in America
30 percent obese over here, and 70 percent normal weight over here
and everybody assumes that the problem is this group over here because
80 percent of the obese population is sick in some fashion
with type-2 diabetes, lipid problems, hypertension, cardiovascular disease, cancer, dementia,
none alcoholic fatty liver disease, polysistical ovarian disease, etc, etc
so, if you do the math on this, that's 80 percent of 30 percent of 240 million, that's 57 million sick
and it's those 57 million that are bankrupting the country
and so it's the obese person's fault only
and that's the way everyone views this
this is wrong, this is a mistake, this is a disaster actually, because it is not correct
here's the real story, in fact, 20 percent of the obese population is completely metabolically normal
they have normal insulin dynamics, they don't get sick,
they will live a completely normal life, die at a completely normal age,
cost the taxpayer nothing, they're just fat
conversely, up to 40 percent of the normal weight population have the exact same metabolic dysfunction
that the obese do, they are just normal weight, and so they don't even know they are sick, until it's too late
because, normal weight people get type-2 diabetes, they get hypertension, they get dyslipidemia, they get cardiovascular disease, they get cancer, they get dementia, etc, etc
and so when you do the math on that, that's another 67 million, so that's actually outclassing the obese, and so the total is 124 million, that's more than half of all of America
Now, you may remember HIV
Remember HIV? When did HIV become a public health crisis?
No, not in the 80s
In the, in 1991
1991, 1979 patient zero, so we first learned about the, you know
the diagnoses, throughout the entire 80s it was all about the gays and the attics (?)
and it was always, it's their problem, their personal responsibility, their behavior, their fault
and then something happened in 1991, anybody remember what it was?
Magic Johnson, Magic Johnson got HIV
and all of a sudden everyone went "Holly Mother…" you know what
and everybody realized, you know what? everyone's at risk, and all of a sudden it became a public health crisis
so when does a personal responsibility issue become a public health crisis? and that's what we're gonna talk about tonight
because this is a public health crisis
here's the slide that demonstrates the phenomenon
so here are two equally weighted adult men
which one's healthy and which one's sick
anybody know?
the one on the bottom is sick, right, he's sick
why? All that visceral fat, all that fat surrounding the organs
see this guy over here he's got big love handles, but you know, so what
in fact, this is perfectly healthy, it's no problem, because subcutaneous fat is actually kinda good for you
there are actually studies that show more subcutaneous fat, more longevity
whereas this stuff, this is the bad stuff, this is the poison stuff over here
so, the fact is, standing on a scale doesn't tell you where your fat is
what does?
well your weight ??? is a good start, and then there's some lab tests you can do as well, the bottom line is there are a lot of normal weight people who have this phenomenon called TOFI
Thin in the outside fat on the inside
ok? Probably some right here in the audience
and they get type-2 diabetes, they get dyslipidemia, they get hypertension, etc, etc, you get the picture?
everyone's at risk, because everyone's exposed, the question is, what it is you're exposed to?
because obesity is not the problem, it never was
they want you to think it's the problem, but it ain't the problem
what is the problem? Metabolic syndrome is the problem
the cluster of diseases that I've just described you, 'cause that's where all the money goes
obesity cost almost nothing, metabolic syndrome is 75 percent of all health-care costs today
and there's the list right there, everyone with me now? Ok, do I have your attention? Ok
So how does this work? So this actually is a redundancy from the previous Youtube video so I apologize for that
it has to do with how you view the question of obesity and what does it mean, so
of course obesity obeys the first law of thermodynamics, and I don't argue that
the total energy inside a closed system remains constant. It's a law
ok, if I didn't believe in the first law of thermodynamics you'd have me written out on the rail, I'd be the ultimate heretic and zealot and I would be discredited
of course I believe in the first law of thermodynamics, it's a law
the question is, as I've learned from my legal training, who's truth, which interpretation
you know the Supreme Court always comes down 5-4 on everything, right, right?
True, ok, because there are two interpretations, I mean, basically that's what the Supreme Court ???, interpreting the law
the law is the law, but the interpretation is something else, so here are the two interpretations
If you eat it, you better burn it, or you gonna store it
if that's true, then this is a matter of energy balance
energy balance, that's what everyone will tell you
and it's the result of two aberrant behaviors, calories in - gluttony, calories out - sloth
and that's what everybody assumes, is, if you're obese, well you must eat too much or exercise too little, or both
and therefore, it's your fault
and that's what we believe and to this day we still don't have insurance for obesity
although just today, you know that the AMA finally said "obesity is a disease"
so it's funny, because actually in 2004 HHS said obesity is a disease
it took the AMA 9 years to catch up with HHS, figure that out
so the do… it's based on this dogma, the dogma is, that if you eat more than you burn you'll gain weight, if you eat less than you burn you'll lose weight
because all calories are the same, a calorie is a calorie
this is the biggest… pile of you-know-what there is
this is absolute not true
but if you believe it then the corollaries of a calorie is a calorie are
that this is free will, you get to choose what you get to put in your mouth, it's personal responsibility because if you are obese you chose to be
gluttony and sloth that is your problem and diet and exercise will fix it
that's what everyone believes from a calorie is a calorie
and who says that a calorie is a calorie, well?
the food industry says a calorie is a calorie, and that's 'cause it serves them well, so this is the fiction
this is Coca-Cola coming together video on Youtube
released just before the Superbowl, that says: "Beating obesity will take action by all of us based on one simple common sense fact"
common sense fact, all calories count, no matter where they come from, including Coca-cola and everything else with calories, a calorie is a calorie
why pick on Coca-cola, why pick on Burger King, why pick on any individual
because it serves them well, because it diffuses the issue
so, is that what we've got? We've just gut a caloric bachanalia? Oh, sorry, wait, this is wrong, that's better, ok
Indeed we are all eating more, I don't argue that, 187 calories per day more for men,
335 calories per day more for women, 275 calories more per day for teen boys
than 25 years ago, we are all eating more, I don't argue that, of course we are, question is why
so you'd say, well this is why, this is the evolution of fast food over here, 1957 we had the original White Castle hamburger, 210 calories right there, 1 ounce
over here we have today's Bob's Big Boy over here at 618 calories
and of course in the midst of the obesity epidemic hardies (?) had the temerity to offer us the Thickburger at 1420 calories
and of course you can go to Carls' Junior and get the 6$ burger, which is 2000 calories, that's the entire caloric allotment for the day
and people are proud to go doit, right?
How? Anybody here had a Trenta?
A Trenta, yes, no? Ok, so that's this guy over here
so it's not hot coffee, it's a cold coffee drink
flavored with you-know-what, and it is 916 cc
well, your stomach is 900cc, it's bigger than your stomach
so you'd say, well there's your answer, Q.E.D, it's all over right?
How about this? I love this, it's came in the mail
"Free chicken sandwich from KFC with the purchase of a 30 ounce drink"
the food's gotten so cheap we're are giving it away? That's where we are, ok
Or is it the opposite side of the equation? Is it an activity famine?
So this is a study that was done looking at physical activity here on the Y axis
against age, 9-years old to 19-years old, for white girls and black girls
so you can see that by the time they hit age 15 the black girls are just lying prostrate on the floor
'cause there's no physical activity whatsoever
so you say, well there's your answer, that's why everyone's obese
because they're eating too much and they're exercising too little, gluttony and sloth, diet and exercise
just like common sense tells you
well, you know what? I don't believe in common sense, I believe in data
Ok? And that's why we do research
because education consists mainly of what we have unlearned
in fact, if everything that we knew were true, there would be no reason for research, would there?
I would never have to do any research 'cause everything we knew was already right
In fact, everything we learned 10 years ago is already wrong, and everything we know today will be wrong 10 years from now
and that's why you do research, and the fact is the research tells us something very different
so, is this behavior, is this personal responsibility? what do you think
there are 6 reasons to doubt this
Number 1: no child chooses to be obese
the quality of an obese… life of an obese child is the same as a patient on cancer chemotherapy
why would anyone choose this, in fact, children are ostracized
Does, second, does diet work? Now everybody knows somebody who lost weight on a diet
and then of course they gained it all back, and that's what all the data shows
and the number of people who can actually maintain their weight loss for any length of time is vanishingly small
and if it weren't true you wouldn't be sitting here listening to me, because you'd say, well why do I have to listen to him?
Does exercise work? So,
here are studies of exercise and this is the identity line here and you can see when compared with no treatment exercise resulted in very small weight loss across the board
one BMI point, bigger exercise 1.5 BMI points
considering, we are all 7 to 8 BMI points more than we should be
you know, that ain't gonna cut it, because exercise does not cause weight loss. Does not cause weight loss.
What does exercise do? It causes muscle gain, and that's good
because muscles have mitochondria, mitochondria burn energy
so you stay insulin sensitive because you have a place to put your energy instead of in your liver where it causes problems
so, exercise is the single best thing you can do for yourself, but if you think it's gonna show up on the scale, think again
So when you stand on the scale, what are you measuring? You're measuring 4 compartments at once
Bone, more is better
Muscle, more is better
Subcutaneous fat, more is better, I just showed you
and finally visceral fat, more is worse
Now the visceral fat usually ac compasses about 4 to 6 percent of your total body weight
so when you stand on the scale, what are you measuring? You don't know, you can't possibly know
So, we have all these doctors telling their patients, well if you'd only exercise you'd lose weight, and then of course they don't
because they've built muscle, which is good, but it doesn't show up on the scale
and then they get depressed, because, oh, I was doing this to lose weight and it didn't work, and so I might as well stop because obviously it doesn't work for me
this is the single most egregious thing doctors do to their patients today, and as far as I'm concerned, that's almost malpractice
because the data say otherwise
Number 3, this isn't just about America
and it's not just about UK, it's not just about Australia, yes we are the 3 fattest countries
and we spent the least amount of our GDP on food, that's true
but it's going on everywhere, every country, every single country on the planet has shown an uptick in obesity
some have shown an uptick in diabetes and some have shown a downtick
but for obesity, everybody's going up, doesn't matter where you look, every country has shown an increase
Number 4, the poor are disproportionately affected
and they don't have access to choices, they can't even leave their house for fear of crime
how they'gonna exercise, how they're gonna let their kids out, to go play in the yard, when they might, you know, face a straight bullet
they don't have a supermarkets, they live in food desserts, so if you don't have a choice, how can you call it personal responsibility?
You know, this is one of the most egregious, pejorative statements that there is
Number 5, the prevalence of obesity is going up in the group
that you can least ascribe personal responsibility to, the toddler
the 2-5 year old group is going up the fastest, you wanna say that that's personal respons… oh you say
the personal responsibility of the parent, right, for letting them have the sugar pops and
and you know, and the sodas, and the fruit juices, and everything else is, parents' fault
except for one thing, we've been having an epidemic of obese 6 months olds, and they don't diet and exercise
so any hypothesis you wanna proffer, you have to explain this as well
and it's even worse than that, because we have obesity in newborns
newborns, ok? Birth weights gone up by 200 grams all over the world
all over the world over the last 25 years, and when you look at, when you do dexa scans to figure out what the body composition is
it's all fat, it's all fat
so there, these babies are laying down more fat before they're ever born and fat cells wanna get filled
that's why we have obese 6 months old, because everybody is laying down more fat, so the question is how? Why?
Why they are laying down more fat today?
Most clearly, mother's diet
But you wanna blame the newborn for that problem?
Is that their problem? Is that their fault?
So you wanna blame the pregnant mother? Well you know… then, just go backwards like that, so basically blame everybody
or blame nobody, I blame nobody. Actually I do blame somebody but you're gonna get there by the end
So we are talking about behavior, right? Behavior, so this is the definition of behavior, this is all from the original video
A stereotyped motor response to a physiological stimulus, so let's take that apart
Stereotyped, same every time, so, yes, eating is a behavior
motor, muscles have to move, a thought is not a behavior
and finally, physiological, and that's where I come in
What's the physiology behind the obesity epidemic? Why do you eat too much and exercise too little?
Because all behaviors have a biochemical basis
Now sometimes we are smart enough to know what it is and sometimes we are not smart enough to know what it is
give you an example: schizophrenia
For a 100 years schizophrenia was behavioral disorder, now we know it's a defect in dopamine neuro transmission, and probably actually a defect in glucose transport across the brain
Ok? These are biochemical problems, that ultimately manifest themselves as a behavioral disorder, this is no different
So what are the biochemical underpinnings behind gluttony and sloth? That's the question, and that's what we're gonna try to answer now
So in order to answer that we have to know some science, and I'm gonna make this very brief and very quick
We're gonna talk about these two hormones right over here, called leptin and insulin
so leptin is a hormone that comes from your fat cell, goes to your brain and tells your brain, you have enough energy on board, to engage in normal, expensive metabolic processes
you can burn energy at a normal rate and feel good doing it
ok? And tells your brain, you've got enough energy on board, if your leptin goes down, or if your brain doesn't see your leptin, then your brain sees that as starvation
Everybody got that?
Insulin is equally interesting, because insulin tells your fat cell one thing, it says, store energy
and it tells your brain something else, it tells your brain: stop